so
[Music]
yes
manulife and china bank
two companies you can trust two top
institutions in the financial industry
teammates partners working together to
handle
every aspect of your finances from day
to day
to your future plans personalized to
your story
so you're ready for life's every twist
and turn
we have you covered starting with your
kids dreams
to providing a secure future for your
family
working to build your wealth and
ensuring your wealth
works for you always with you in
sickness and in health
through the best times and the worst all
just for you
let us be your partner manulife china
bank life
life with a plan let us help you get
started
today
you deserve the best life you work hard
you know the formula for success
your options are wide but few make the
cut
we can help you make the most out of
life
because you deserve the privilege that
comes with building an elite life
introducing manulife china bank life
affluence max
elite this one-time investment in life
insurance plan
provides you with a startup bonus that
would optimize your funds on the onset
so you can enjoy rewards now and in the
future
experience the manulife china bank life
advantage
let's say you put in a one-time
investment of 1 million pesos
manulife china bank life will give you
one percent of that
as a startup bonus this increases your
investment by 10
000 pesos get a loyalty bonus
if you stay invested you may have the
chance to get a loyalty bonus
on the 10th 15th and on the 20th year
enjoy hassle-free application through a
guaranteed issue offer
this means that there would be no need
for medical examinations
if certain conditions are met
get a boost on your investment by making
additional investments
anytime enjoy peace of mind with life
insurance coverage
invest through manulife china bank life
affluence
max elite get an early reward
and look forward to more
manulife and china bank
two companies you can trust two top
institutions in the financial industry
teammates partners working together to
handle every aspect of your finances
from day to day to your future plans
personalized to your story
so you're ready for life's every twist
and turn
we have you covered starting with your
kids dreams
to providing a secure future for your
family
working to build your wealth and
ensuring your wealth works for you
always with you in sickness and in
health through the best times
and the worst all just for you let us be
your partner
manulife china bank life life with a
plan
let us help you get started today
you deserve the best life you work hard
you know the formula for success
your options are wide but few make the
cut we can help you make the most
out of life because you deserve the
privilege
that comes with building an elite life
introducing manulife china bank life
affluence max
elite this one-time investment in life
insurance plan
provides you with a startup bonus that
would optimize your funds on the onset
so you can enjoy rewards now and in the
future
experience the manulife china bank life
advantage
let's say you put in a one-time
investment of one million pesos
manulife china bank life will give you
one percent of that
as a start-up bonus this increases your
investment by
10 000 pesos get a loyalty bonus
if you stay invested you may have the
chance to get a loyalty bonus
on the 10th 15th and on the 20th year
enjoy hassle-free application
through a guaranteed issue offer
this means that there would be no need
for medical examinations
if certain conditions are met
get a boost on your investment by making
additional investments
anytime enjoy peace of mind with life
insurance coverage
invest through manulife china bank life
affluence
max elite get an early reward
and look forward to more
[Music]
good afternoon everyone while waiting
for our program to start
may we invite everyone to answer our
poll questions flashed on your screens
right now
[Music]
thank you to everyone who answered for
those who haven't sent your votes in yet
please don't close the form and submit
your answers now
stay tuned for a raffle draw later mcpl
will be raffling off
[Music]
something to the forward thank you
good afternoon again everyone i am wami
haveliana
welcoming you to mcbl's growing wealth
beyond borders do you know that there
are different types of
investments my personal favorite is an
investment linked
life insurance program because this plan
gives life protection coverage and the
possibility of higher returns in the
future
this is also known as a variable unit
link plan
or a vul plan now some of these vol
plans can provide a stream of income
payouts that you may use for emergency
purposes
along with that you have the freedom to
choose
where you want to invest a portion of
your premium
it can be invested locally globally
or even across asset classes
and investing in offshore funds can
offer you a host of benefits from
increased protection of your wealth to
potential tax advantages
i'm sure you'll want to hear more about
this
that's why we invited two subject matter
experts this afternoon
our first guest will help us understand
what investment link
life insurance is about and how it can
help us earn and save more
when we invest in offshore funds our
second guest
will talk about the market outlook for
and manulife fund performance
throughout the program if you have
comments or questions
for our speakers go ahead and feel free
to send them via the q
a box at the bottom right hand side of
your screen
later on our guests will address these
questions or some comments
in the q a session okay now
let's get right into the meat of the
program by introducing our first
speaker he is the president and ceo of
ramveer financials
a serial entrepreneur with companies and
endeavors in multiple industries
he is the lead independent director of
globe telecom
and of ayala land logistics holdings
holdings corporation
he is an independent director for ayala
land and for the national
reinsurance corporation he is also the
chairman of the salvivo funds and the
director of esquire financing
seed box technologies the blue leaf the
kolinin group
and the mobile group inc to name a few
he is also a best-selling author and a
business
leadership and financial advisor and
mentor
ladies and gentlemen please welcome
mr rex mendoza
good afternoon thank you so much for
that introduction
thank you and thanks to everyone for
being with us
you elected to make us part of your day
it's a friday afternoon
and there are a lot of things to do on a
friday afternoon
but you chose to be here and for that
reason
it is our job to make this an
enlightening
learning experience for all of you and
hopefully
there would be very valuable insights
and takeaways
that you're gonna get out of this so
my topic is growing wealth beyond
borders
is it a good time to talk about this
there's been
you know a lot of debate on that you
think about investments rex at this
particular time
why aren't we supposed to like just
hold on to whatever we have make sure
that we're pretty safe
and wait for the dust to settle
and to be able to look at opportunities
to invest again
sometime down the road why think about
this
today my next slide will show you
why certainly next slide please
certainly there is always this debate
about
growth and risk it's almost like we can
take growth put it on the back seat at
times when
the economy gets rough we all know
that's not supposed to be the case
because
what we have should be a balancing act
yes
we never control the environment but we
control ourselves
we will have to control our responses to
the environment
and why is that so because achieving
financial objectives
doesn't only happen when the market is
good we have to achieve
the objectives we want to achieve at the
right time
and that's not actually going to be
focused on
good markets alone we have to be able to
hit them right on the mark when they
need to happen
whether the market is good or bad so
regardless of the situation
we have to achieve our goals so the
management
of our finances the management of our
investments
happen whether the market is going well
or not
the other the other point is the fact
that
perspective changes when you have
a very different horizon see many of us
are really scared and concerned because
we're looking at
what's happening today and maybe
that will persist and fester in the next
few months
but think about it end of the year
or even end of next year
the storyline would probably change as
more and more people get vaccinated
so in the end it's a matter of
discipline
and strategy but as i
would like to discuss this nonetheless
there is a must that that will have to
look at
global economies we have to look at how
things
are going so my next slide will tell you
that there are common thematics
that we're gonna see i mean you can hear
this from
you know a fund manager in the
philippines a fund manager
in hong kong or maybe even a fund
manager in the us and the uk
there are four themes that everyone's
going to be having
in terms of business outlooks for 2021
the fact that number one this is going
to be a year of two hubs
why a year of two halves because the
first half of the year will be so
uncertain
we see surges in covid infections
but on top of that we see the start
of the vaccinations we see the start of
the inoculation so
certainly the first half of the year
will be volatile there would be a debate
between people who think things are
going to get better
and people are going to be saying things
are going to get worse and we cannot say
who's going to be correct
between both of them however for the
next part of the year
as we see more and more people get
vaccinated
the storyline will change and obviously
as i get asked by a lot of people
i tell them i'm not exactly a strategic
optimist but i can tell you and i can
you know probably surmise that the last
six months of this year
will be better than the last six months
of last year and why am i saying that
because last year there was no
vaccination
not one individual was vaccinated
in the philippines in 2020. so if you're
going to be looking at 2021
i don't care if it's going to be a
million i don't care if it's going to be
less than 5 of the population but it's
still more
than what we had last year so it will be
better
the next trend and the next thematic
will be
a talk about the k shape recovery yes
we don't talk about v-shaped l-shaped
and u-shaped anymore
it's going to be k-shaped and k-shape is
exactly
you know manifested by this that there
are industries
and companies that are going to be doing
well and there would be those that will
be lagging behind
obviously those are the those are going
to be leading the pack are those that
are in technology
obviously we're all about digital now
because we're stuck to our homes
there would be retail essential retail
and lastly software services however
other businesses and industries like
travel tourism hospitality
you know even those that are concerned
with food services obviously the malls
are closed
they're going to be lagging behind and
it will take a bit of time for them
to recover and follow suit so
you're going to be seeking this concept
called k-shape recovery moving forward
the third thematic will be inflation
yes governments are pumping cheap money
into their systems they're going to
you know in the philippines we call it
ayuda
but in other places it's a
stimulus it's a handout it's cheap money
given by governments to alleviate you
know the plight for their citizens
that will be inflationary no matter what
we do that's going to be inflationary
which leads us to the 4 thematic would
be
which would be the quest for yields
certainly you will be worse off if
you're going to be putting money
just solely in low yielding and say
financial instruments
because obviously inflation will be
eating most part of that kind of value
so technically you're going to be losing
money while you keep it
and that's the reason why there is a
quest
for better yields while people are
looking at
somehow a reasonably
you know risk-laden instrument that they
can still manage
so these are the fortimatics but what is
driving the global economy
the global economy is going to be seeing
a surge this year obviously last year
was the most pessimistic part
of the last five years next slide please
i am going to
you know probably assume that
different countries will obviously be
bouncing
off from that low and when you bounce
from that low
what happens there would be strong
recovery
before it simmers down and normalizes in
so what are the common common
issues that will be present and will be
you know the order of the day for many
countries as i mentioned
continue stimulus support but the
sovereign debt stock will increase
because
you know countries don't have that kind
of money not all countries do
and we're just one of those we will have
to borrow if we're going to be
increasing the level of help
and the level of aid that we're going to
be giving our countrymen
we will have to borrow this and many
countries are like us
there would be a compounding difficulty
a compounded difficulty in our debt
service
and we see that in many countries but
it's all
sovereign so basically if it's going to
be internally sourced
then it's going to be fine but many
countries like the philippines would not
be sourcing dollar loans or loans from
you know outside their jurisdictions
which means their balance sheets are
going to be imperiled
as a country there are question marks
with regard to that kind of practice
but the push will be for virus uh the
virus control imperative
the vaccinations and certainly on the
industry side
a restructuring for productivity so
if you're going to be looking at it in
in in summary there would be three
drivers
three things that were you know on the
lookout for the global economy next
slide please
and these three things are as follows i
mean sorry
this is the growth rate for the global
marketplace um global would be at around
5.2 you'll see the
united states at around 3.1 in 2021
you're going to see the highest numbers
where in asia
in asia we're expected to rebound and
that would be a
solid a solid 8 percent however
that's predominantly driven
not by the philippines but by china
china is part of this group
and china is actually pulling this group
up and i will show you later on
the kind of numbers china has so
basically
this is a global trend it's all about
growth
and as i've said very strong growth at
the start
simmering down at the tail end of 2021
and probably
2022. so again the three things
that would be driving the 2021 first
half expectations would be the next
slide
the economic rebound is going to
accelerate
it's going to be all about trend because
obviously the
the baseline for last year was really
low uh we were starting from the crash
of 2020 march
and obviously from from this year first
quarter to that year moving on to the
second quarter there are many
places where you know you can just
imagine i've
mentioned china the growth in the china
gdp is fantastic
you know it's it's over 18 it's 18.3
uh that's not exactly the same way for
the philippines because we got ourselves
into
another surge and because we did
a strict lockdown starting march again a
year
after we did it last year we were kind
of pulled back as far as the economic
rebound is concerned
high liquidity through fiscal and
monetary stimulus that will persist
as i've said they won't care about
inflation they will help
their you know suffering population many
countries will do that
and lastly turbo charge structural
trends
so we're going to be all about digital
it's going to be all about
all online sustainable investing is
going to be
a focus as well and e-commerce
so there would be as mentioned
revenge spending and maybe revenge
traveling
for some of the other countries
unfortunately
let me mention this for the philippines
it's going to be a bit delayed
that would be what we call a reality
bite scenario
next slide please where the philippines
is
going to lag behind now i am not saying
we're not going to recover
we are going to recover it's just that
we're going to be
a bit delayed than many others including
those countries
that are our asean neighbors so our
restart and recovery may take longer
than expected
we backtrack because of uh the ecq
and the surge that we've seen we're
recovering from that hopefully
this would be a continuous opening up uh
and then we don't have to pull back from
there
the recent infection surge has really
impacted our recovery trajectory
now the question is this the pace of
vaccinations
taking much lower than ideal and is a
need for
acceleration just imagine the kind of
vaccinations we're having
currently it's all lgu driven
the private sector is not in the ball
game maybe they'll start doing that
they'll start being in the game by about
june or july
but i guess clearly if you think about
10 000 vaccinations in any given day
we're probably going to be hitting what
1 million by the end of the year and
that's basically just one percent of our
population
that's very very far from what we want
to have which is herd immunity
and herd immunity is 70 percent of the
population
and as we speak there are countries that
are very close to that already
and you will see the trend in their
infection so basically
you know a very sad story for the
philippines but again
i will always say there would be a
bright time
maybe you and i cannot just pin it down
but it will happen
but it will get pushed back and as
investors
we'll have to do something about it we
will have to do something about it
next slide please you will see that
picture
of that surge that's very real
it has happened and i guess what's
telling
is the next slide if you are going to be
looking at that other chart
you're going to see us getting compared
to our neighbors indonesia singapore
thailand
myanmar and vietnam next slide please
you will see
us getting compared to those other
countries in terms of new cases
in terms of new cases so while the other
countries around us are increasing their
level of vaccinations where infections
are getting lower
the philippines suddenly got into a
second
search starting march hopefully things
are simmering down today
but since the vaccinations aren't in the
ideal pace
we are going to be seeing this to be a
persistent
issue so how does that impact our market
take note of what has happened to our
market from a very very confident
january
next slide please a very very confident
january you will see us drop
15 okay and that's off
friday i mean if you're going to be
looking at you know
that kind of a drop is 15 that's just
the start of january january we were
thinking
this year is better but all of a sudden
a drop of 15
because march and april weren't as good
again we went back
to those stricter lockdowns but let me
put things in perspective this is where
i sometimes see people needing the kind
of
information needing the kind of
confidence boost
because people sometimes don't look at
investment horizons correctly
when you're going to be looking at
short-term gyrations like this
it will essentially spook you but if
you're going to be looking a bit farther
next slide please you're going to say
hey 15
drop that follows a 53
recovery from the drop we have in march
2020 that was a
53 increase
so a 15 retracement from that
is not exactly bad markets don't have to
go
up on a very parabolic mode
parabolic recoveries are not sustainable
so the market always has a reason for
correcting a bit to gather more muscle
to grow again it just became
so comfortable and then so timely that
a surge happened then it gave people a
you know probable reason to expect the
market to correct
but on top of that you know we have to
talk turkey here we have to talk
facts much of the reason also for the
drop is an msei rebalancing so
it's not exactly economy driven
it's actually an investment you know
platform and an investment index
drive many of our companies were lowered
the philippines exactly you know had to
be sold down by foreign fund managers
because some of our companies
got a lower weighting in that index and
as you know it if foreign fund managers
sell our markets go down because we
don't have
that kind of volume so that's the
reality that we'll have to contend with
so you'll have to see that that growth
isn't
exactly that bad that has to be a
correction that follows it
if you're going to be seeing
projections in gdp which is the next
slide
um you will see that we're also supposed
to have our own search right
but that's going to happen on the
third quarter cannot be the first
quarter the first quarter
still had a good january in february
last year why we had the
eruption january and february of last
year
were open economies
for two months we only had that that
quarantine restriction by march
however going into 2021
we had a you know relatively open but
still not the same way as january
february of last year
but a bad march so that's the reason why
you see
still a negative compared to last year
in fact the expectation was
negative 5.4 we're only minus 4.2 so
it's still
you know higher than expected but
hopefully the third quarter will give us
a good bump
and that will simmer down to about five
percent growth by the fourth quarter
next slide please so the quest for
investors
shall always be resilient we all have to
have resilience
it is the capacity to recover quickly
from difficulties
and the capability to thrive despite the
odds
we can never make an excuse
out of the economy for our financial
goals
you're still going to educate your
children you're still going to give them
the great education
they they they deserve whether or not
markets are good or bad
you're still gonna retire at a certain
age
at a certain year whether that
trajectory has been laden with
bumps like a covet pandemic
so the the recourse is not to look
outside and see what's
happening but to look inside and see how
we maneuver and that gives me you know
the opportunity to discuss the concept
of asset allocation with you
next slide please the concept asset
allocation states that
you know we don't actually invest to
make more money
we invest to achieve financial goals and
since most of those goals are actually
long term
blips like the covet pandemic is always
going to be
part of expectations the volatility the
bumps
like 2008 1997
they will always happen but even if they
do happen
the question becomes what should we do
about it
so if it's a journey where you want the
resilience
you'll have to do something about it
you'll have to focus on the goals
that you want to achieve and the kind of
strategy
that you can have in terms of your
investment
behavior your investment journey that's
going to get us to where we want to go
so what is asset allocation let me
define it for you
next slide please asset allocation is
the investment strategy that
you know invest in different asset
classes
you know you're not supposed to put your
egg in one basket we've learned that
very early
however we also have to know that all of
these
assets don't react
or perform the same way in
any given market scenario time deposits
stocks bonds management real estate
insurance and cash you know have to be
part of a portfolio that balances risk
and reward
based on an investor's risk tolerance
time horizon
and goals and objectives in fact does
that mean
that we're going to be having these
asset classes
only in a given geographic situation
like one country
the philippines or is it high time
we also go out and participate in other
economies
and other markets that might do better
i think that's a question that we'd want
to be able to answer today
but let's look at all of these
considerations let's look at
consideration number one risk appetite
next slide please so
because there is such a thing as a risk
appetite it
will have to be a you know
a conviction amongst all of us that we
have
a degree of comfort in what we want to
invest in
we are going to be you know absorptive
of a certain level of volatility
only but that is what we call
a risk versus return efficient frontier
so much so that you get to increase a
level of risk
then there is a supposedly matched level
of increase in terms of return and you
will see that
over a certain spectrum that that
efficient
you know um frontier is something that
you'll have to hit
and and then take notice off because if
you're just going to be taking
risks excessively then
you might put yourself in a precarious
situation because we all understand
higher risk higher reward so if you're
running for the reward you're actually
taking more of high risk but if you're
going to be
too safe too safe is not good as well
because you're going to be losing on a
consistent basis
because inflation is going to be eating
up
the value or the purchasing power of
your money
and aside from risk appetite we also
have another
major factor also in you know balancing
growth and risk and that's called
you know a time horizon an investment
horizon the term
of your investment next slide please the
time horizon is very important
in a sense that it has to match
your life cycle if you're younger
and the way you've laid it you know
within a journey is that you're going to
hit
certain financial objectives like 10
years 15 years from now
then you can be a little more growth
focused
because you have the time you have the
runway
however if you're about to retire in
three years four years
can you still take that kind of risk
or are we supposed to dial down
on growth instruments and push ourselves
into
defensive instruments so it will now be
a
function not of our risk appetite but
it's also a function of
the soundness of the kind of risk we can
take because of the age that we have
because of the time that we have in
order to
you know hit the goals we want within
our
investment journey so as we we get on
with this
you know next slide please we also have
to realize this one major point and then
this is something that i i give as a
warning to a lot of people
who get to listen to me because you know
as as the markets become more
retail driven next slide please markets
more
are more retail driven people think they
can do diy
all the time or do it yourself where
they can invest in direct stocks they
invest in
you know even offshore instruments by
themselves
you know creating a massive flow of
funds
into self-driven self-decided portfolios
i'd want to be able to tell them hey
it's a fact
90 of people who directly trade lose
money
it's a real fact 90 and and why does
that happen
and why do all the statistics point to
that it's because in reality
any long-term portfolio the performance
is driven by asset allocation
all the researchers i've seen the lowest
is about 65
attributed to asset allocation this
particular research
i'm showing this pie chart will give you
asset allocation driven where security
selection is only five percent
market timing is two percent and other
factors two percent so
why are people taking too much time
trying to invest on their own let me
tell you why
because it's exciting it gives us a lot
of
you know satisfaction whenever we make
moves and you know it just
works for us it's exciting
however because it's our decision
and sometimes when it gets to a fluke we
also sometimes cannot forgive ourselves
for
for doing that and regret always happens
at the tail end of this let me just give
you an example i mean
we all know technology globally
is the thematic to invest on
but you see there is a difference
between a
professional fund manager looking at the
technology space
looking at brands that we all know and
understand
looking at actual performances and even
companies that back them up as retail
players
were only exposed
to the names themselves like microsoft
apple you know tesla you can even
think about very popular names right now
like square
uh companies like those
but you see when it boils down to
fundamentals and people don't know
fundamentals
you will never know what's hyped and
what's real valuation
that's the scary part and if you don't
know that
can you actually
match your future goals with this kind
of an investment practice you know this
morning i just shared
a a particular infographic to a lot of
my friends
as i i do this most of the time if i get
to
um you know get information like that i
i
push it over viber i post it by doing a
youtube
you know video i also do blogs right now
because of
what we're seeing today i mean that's
the only way i can touch base with a lot
of people
and this morning you know what i
mentioned you know for all the other
companies that are now getting the
attention because of technology
you know i i tell them hey don't you
know that apple
is the real name when it comes to real
valuation
and people get surprised because i put
companies like uh
you know um square companies like you
know in a given spectrum
uh the companies that are getting to be
to be so popular
right followed through by the the
pundits what as we call them the
retailers
you know out of a list of 10 companies
apple ip earpods ear parts we're talking
about earpods not even the ipad or the
iphone
the earpods the earpods outsell
more than five of the companies on the
top 10 list
combined just earpods that that just
gives you
the kind of fundamentally driven
sales information that we all need but
again we're not analysts we're not going
to get that every day
but we're going to be investing every
day based on what we hear
and based on what we read and that's
going to be the precarious part
next slide please so diversification is
a must whether you are going to be in
a bull or a bear market you want to
increase your portfolio resiliency
you have to diversify and if
you're not going to get anything from my
whole talk this afternoon
if you're going to forget everything
this is something that i just like you
to remember this is something that i'd
want
to resonate with all of you this next
slide is going to be very busy
but let me explain it next slide please
you're going to
look at this slide and as i've said it's
very busy
these are 16 years 16 years
of markets from 2006 to 2021.
you're going to be looking at the top
square that's the best performing asset
class for the year
so 2021 best performing u.s equity
2006 philippine equity 2013
u.s equity 2018 ux
fixed income so you're going to see
asset classes
that are very different here asian
equity global equity global
fixed income asian fixed income okay
commodities
gold they're all here what does this
tell you
just by looking at the colors there is
no consistent performer
there is no consistent performer and as
i can say
okay the philippines was what top
performer in
four out of the 16 years
it's also a laggard last two places
five times in the last 16 years as well
the worst thing is this from 2018
to 2021 the last four years
the philippines is considered a laggard
last two
trunks on that chart so what does that
tell you
to be exposed in a given market in a
given asset class
is going to be very very dangerous it is
going to be very very dangerous
and it also gets to hamper
your performance especially if you're
not cognizant of your timelines
can you just imagine ladies and
gentlemen you're about to hit
retirement in 2020 and 2021
and you're heavily too heavily involved
in philippine equities
the last four years would have been
detrimental for you
so the key is to do asset allocation the
key is to be involved in other markets
because we don't know what's going to
perform
and we have to make sure that we have
the right diversification
and asset allocation will be the only
thing that gives you that
next slide please look at the global
vaccination campaign
you don't even see the philippines as
part of that slide
so if we're going to be too exposed to a
given market and we're not diversified
then we're always going to be in danger
let me focus on this next slide next
slide please
global growth in 2021 look at it
global growth is going to be on a
consensus 5.7
with fidelity saying that the upside is
6.9 and the low side is 4.1
look at the us 6.2 would be the
consensus and that's going to be between
nine and
five as far as fidelity is concerned
china
eight and a half the median would be
nine
and seven the forecast now is that china
is going to be ending up at a very high
nine
very close to a ten
the philippines will not have these
kinds of numbers this year because
obviously
we're really delayed in our vaccinations
and on top of that we really are
hampered by the kind of surges
that we're experiencing not just in the
metropolis
but in the provinces next slide please
the global markets will actually improve
substantially because of the savings
rate
that is going to be fueling a recovery
you're going to be seeing household
savings rate
the orange to be 2020 and 2021
to be your blue line
so people are saving more money
during this pandemic and that's going to
drive what you call
reverse reverse or revenge spending
reverse or you know revenge travel
moving forward steep accelerations
look at what's happening to the us the
u.s business cycle
next slide please look at that kind of a
an economic index look at their
manufacturing
and non-manufacturing isms
that is going to be the cornerstone of
you know the biden presidency and biden
would like
to fuel this moving forward he wouldn't
really want
a dip and i guess you know the
vaccinations that they're doing in the
us even
giving out you know us as we learned
from from many of the
tidbits that we're getting in terms of
news from the us they're even
doing lotteries and raffles for the
people who are getting vaccinated
you can win a million dollars just by
being vaccinated
in the philippines we want to be
vaccinated we don't even you know
get to get them administered right
moving on to the next slide look at the
u.s business cycle
consumer spending and retail sales as
expected
because of the reopening look at the
personal
income by component i mean those charts
are very powerful
and their main main competitor now for
the global economy is china
and china is holding on its own
i guess everything started with china
right as we're talking about this cobit
pandemic
so who recovered first obviously china
as well
i mean i don't i don't know but you
probably read about all of those
conspiracy
conspiracy theories but whether they're
true or not doesn't really matter
china economy wise is standing on solid
ground today
next slide please look at the new
robust structural drivers underpinning
the new china
consumption upgrade driven by the rising
middle class and increasing urbanization
rate they're now becoming
driven by their mega cities and i guess
we see surges as they open up
the hermes outlet in shanghai
registered by far the highest
single sales or revenue generating day
globally
in recent times because of opening up i
mean that's
the revenge spending i was talking about
technology in china is an enabler
and it's actually creating new business
models with
10 cent wechat alibaba and all that
moving forward look at the numbers of
china look at gdp
next slide please look at the gdp as
i've said
first quarter 18.3
that simmers down to nine seven and five
but the average of that is 9.8
and you see a surging industrial
production growth
once countries open up china will be
ready
to supply the world with its goods
with its production because it's doing
them today
the inventory levels are rising
there is also a backdrop for a solid
consumption recovery
next slide please for china itself
they're not going to be dependent
on exports alone they're going to be
focused on their own internal markets
look at the kind of household savings
that we're looking at
as of now 37
even before kovit the philippines did
not hit
a savings rate of 20 that's uh
that's unbelievable for us it's going to
be incredible when we get to hit that
but china is hitting it on a normal clip
look at the kind of unemployment
rate you know decrease that you're
seeing there
so they're building up and expanding as
we
speak the growth as mentioned gdp
breakdown would be a nine and the
expectation for 2022
will be between six to seven which is
still
a major a big number you know
knowing the kind of base that they have
so although ladies and gentlemen what
should we be doing
what should we be doing i guess it's a
comprehensive way
of really managing our wealth
comprehensive way of managing our
personal net worth
and estate values let's next slide
please
so if we're going to be seeing this is
the way we should go
we have to look at everything that we
have and we have to focus
that balancing growth and risk tax
leakages and treatment
access and liquidity and distribution
wealth management is a full-scale needs
based management
that assists individuals and families
in three stages accumulation
preservation and transfer of wealth
by customizing the right product
solutions to meet goals and objectives
and i guess you've been invited here
by your friend from mcbl
why because it's a very good time
to think about doing something about
this
when you haven't done enough it would be
a time
to revisit the strategies that we're
making
in order to get our investment
journey on track so
let us look at how we have
really allocated our assets
across multi-classes and markets
next slide please and we don't have to
wait
are you going to wait for things to get
better
let me show you what's happening to the
us right now
that kind of graph will tell you next
chart please
that kind of graph will tell you how
vaccines work
that's the kind of drop in terms of
infections you're gonna see
because they're really making their
vaccinations available
everywhere and within reach by everyone
and it's not just the us next slide
please look at the uk
look at the vaccination rate of the uk
the blue
on the left hand portion of your screen
and the blue
at the right hand portion of your screen
look at that kind
of drop in terms of
infections it's going to be
fast it's going to be swift if you don't
move today
you're going to be left behind so the
key
is acting upon the stimulus and the
information we all have
you know i i mentioned this this this
quote comes from john templeton
one of the pillars and then hallmarks of
the mutual fund industry
and he has said that bull markets are
born in pessimism
they grow in skepticism
they actually mature in optimism
and they die on euphoria you have to be
ahead of the curve
and we've seen this many many times i've
seen this in in
in the 1997 asian crisis i've seen it in
the 2008
global financial crisis four or five
years later what do my friends say
sayong rex no i should have invested in
2008.
saiyan i should have been bested in
1997.
those are the two words we often hear
four or five years
after a crisis sayang sana
and we're going to be hearing that three
to five years from now
because that's real history repeats
itself endlessly for people
who are not willing to learn from the
lessons of the past next slide please
we don't learn from the lessons of the
past
it's such a waste that we went through
them we should be able
to pick up the pieces and move forward
and the best way to do that
as wami mentioned may be to put yourself
in an investment instrument that will
have a best
of two worlds that are very important to
us and in our financial journey moving
forward
next slide please and that's the bul
policy
video policy gives you both the
insurance coverage
and the investment proposition i know
that
for some of you this product would
probably been
having been given a bad press
but that's okay i mean i understand
obviously there can be naysayers
in any given situation but i can say
this
without batting an eyelash there is no
perfect investment instrument
that it's just one scene one one one
something out there
one investment instrument out there that
matches you and your need at this
particular time
that's very important and for what is
ever said about the vol policy
it just tells you that it carries
a downside cover which is your life
insurance
and the propensity to earn more
because it because of its investment
proposition
and i guess the most important part here
would be the choices it gives you
next slide please because of this
combination you will be having many
different uses for this
and you don't even have to decide what
that use is because
you can have that option later on to
swing it
to a child's education make sure it can
give you guaranteed income when you
retire
and all of these other needs that can be
there
once you get into forks on your road in
terms of your financial journey
it will give you the discipline the
diversification
the help of investment expertise because
that investment component is driven by
people
who have it as a 24-hour job
they are trained they are educated to
invest and they
are on the ground compared to us that
probably would be doing many other
things
and we're not even attached to the
market itself so we're going to be
quite delayed in terms of an information
access
and we're also going to be having issues
when it comes to
other things like currency you know uh
credit exposure and stuff like that
on top of it will be service
this is not a combo from your fast food
chain
in mcdonald's you buy a combo and you
consume it in less than an hour that's
the reason why you don't need
follow-through service
from mcdonald's itself but for a
financial product that will be there for
at the very least five years
to 20 years and even more you need the
follow-through you need the guidance
you need the investment advice coming
from someone
who has it as a profession and as a
full-time job
that's a reason why service is a great
great component
of that and that's the reason why i
i guess i i find it very important to
say that
that's one of the biggest benefit you're
not buying a product
you're buying what a product does for
you but on top of that you're also
buying
the service of that expert
that invited you this afternoon
and on top of it you're also buying the
discipline to go with it
because people who opted to do this on
their own
eventually don't actually have the
discipline to follow through
so in cases where they go for the more
efficient cost effective direction
they lose out on the total benefit
because the discipline wasn't there
the other extras will also get to be
discussed with you
that can be riders called critical
illness riders that can also
match you up with health issues and
stuff like that and other benefits
moving forward next slide please
all i can say is this that diversity
reduces adversity
diversification is a must asset
allocation is a must
and you really have to consider this
moving forward
2021 and even 2022 will be challenging
years
these are all going to be challenging
years and
next slide please diversification and
selectivity
pivots in business this will be
strategic anchors for
both this year and next year again
selectivity
diversification in investments pivots
and repurposing in business
we have to be nimble we have to app with
the information that we have in front of
us
and we have to know how to maneuver
in the fulfillment of our financial
dreams
and most importantly doing that
for the people we love and that's the
reason why i always end with this light
next slide please i always end with this
slide
that i ask people you don't invest for
yourself
you don't invest only to achieve
the goals you want as an individual
you're doing this for people you love
you're doing this for special people in
your life
so you have to anchor everything that
you do in your investing
with a special people in your life
because if you do that
you're never going to be wanting in
terms of inspiration you're never going
to be wanting in terms of
motivation you're always going to be
grounded
you're always going to be in that
direction
that forges discipline
makes you make the right decisions
because at the end of the day
it's not the money we get it's a
fulfillment achievements
of the dreams we've set for the very
people
we live for it's not all about
having funds to live on but making sure
those funds are going to be correct
and right for the fun to live for and we
think about that
we think about special people not just
ourselves
but the people we love with that ladies
and gentlemen i
end my presentation i will be back later
on for a q a
but in the meantime i'll be bringing or
handing the floor back to wami habiliana
for uh the next parts of this event
thank you so much
and good afternoon
[Music]
hey good afternoon again everyone
uh thank you rex we appreciate your
insights and how we can benefit
from insurance plans that are linked
uh to offshore funds we will see more of
you later during the q a segment
um if there's one thing i remembered
from your talk
you really mentioned that it is
dangerous to remain
in one asset class and in one geography
at this point in time
so to the audience if you have any
questions for rex
please just type them in the q a box at
the bottom half of your screen and he
will answer them later during our q a
session
so now before we move on to our second
speaker let's check out the
audience's pulse on our paul questions
earlier
it's very nice to see that our audience
today
is very interested in the topic
now our first question was why are you
saving up for investing
so there were three you know answers no
retirement
wealth diversification growth and or
health emergencies
and the top pick was letter a
50 of the audience are saving up for the
retirement so everybody wants to enjoy
their life after work
mcbl has insurance plans that can
actually act
as retirement funds these plans
guarantee lifetime insurance protection
for you and your family
while securing your hard-earned money
with regards to the other
needs wealth diversification and growth
and health emergencies
mcbl also has other products suited for
these needs
in terms of all of these needs we can
say we have got you
covered now let's look at the second
question
where are you currently invested in now
there are a number of answers letter a
to g
m it's very interesting that
31 of you said insurance very
interesting
so that means if you're in currently not
invested or you know if you're if you're
not currently investing your savings are
hard earned
money now is the time to do so
investment in investment linked
insurance programs can see
the potential for your money to grow
please spend time consult a financial
sales associate to help you assess the
right product suited for your needs
if you guys can spend time to do other
things
you might want to spend a lot more time
doing your retirement planning
as half of you have already done lastly
our third question
do you want do you know how life
insurance or
investment life insurance works
yes or no no and a resounding 85 percent
answered yes but of course after hearing
the segment of mr mendoza
i would probably guess that's close to
almost perfect
or 100 so once again
we thank you all our audience to who
those who participated in our activity
earlier
moving on to update us with the latest
market outlook and manulife fund
performance
let me introduce to you our next speaker
he is the head of wealth sales of
manulife investment management and trust
corporation
he has more than 20 years of experience
in retail banking and wealth management
is a chartered wealth manager a
registered financial planner
an sec certified fixed income salesman
and an sec certified investment
solicitor
join me in welcoming mr cedric matubis
[Music]
thank you thank you ami for that guy
introduction good afternoon everyone i
hope
everyone is safe today and enjoying the
webinar so far so before i go to the
outlook let's do a very quick scan
of the fun performance of the of a few
of the vf funds of mcbl as you can see
from this table
one word is key and that word is
divergent so you can
clearly see the difference between the
performance of the
funds invested in the philippine economy
against the funds invested outside of
the philippine economy and there was a
chart that mr mendoza showed you earlier
that that is in line with what's
happening here and uh and and clearly
um there is a there's a big difference
so if you look at the year-to-date
performance for example as of may
13 2021 or end of last week
you can see here that all of the funds
invested in the philippine economy
is still negative while the ones
invested outside of the philippine
economy they're positive and if you look
at the full year
everybody's positive but it's clear that
the offshore funds are already
double-digit while the philippine funds
are not no
and for example you can see here uh our
clients who invested in gtif uh enjoyed
a one full year performance of 21
our clients in appi or asia pacific
property income fund enjoyed a return of
almost
uh last year and asia first in asian
growth uh they're doing spectacularly
well both about forty percent for the
last
year uh while the philippine funds are
not doing as well
they're they have recovered but like uh
what mr mendoza showed earlier we're not
really seeing spectacular returns as
compared to their
offshore counterparts now will these
funds continue to perform well
and to help answer that question let's
look at our outlook on investing in
after covert 19. and uh before i discuss
this i'd like to believe that there are
changes that has happened in the past
few
months uh particularly brought about by
covet and these changes will certainly
transform our lives
in permanent ways and therefore they
will stick with us
even after the pandemic and these
changes i can summarize into three
themes
and uh their effect on the economy and
the markets and also how
people can benefit from them from these
changes so let's go to the first
change and the first theme and the first
theme is on the next like this
technological disruption and
in this theme we i will mention one
major change and what that first
major change is the great office exodus
or the people
more and more people working from home
so before kovid
less than a quarter of people were
reported to be working from home
but after kovid it reports are showing
that around 37 percent
or even up to as high as half of the
employees are all working from home to
some extent and
in fact in certain uh occupations like
legal
business education and finance they have
reported around 88
of their uh workforce working from home
so this is really
um a big impact uh on on on technology
on the demand for data et cetera et
cetera and for the demand for
or the lowering of demand in terms of
office space or real estate so that this
has that impact as well
the second change on this theme is on
the next slide and it's called
it's about spending and we see that more
money is spent
inside the house or at home or on the
home rather than spent outside of the
home
so this trend actually in the u.s
started as early as 2004
but kovit has increased the gap
tremendously as you can see from the
chart the discrepancy between the green
and the blue line green being online
sales and blue being sales happening in
the in department stores
and i i believe that this is um is very
similar to what we're experiencing in
the philippines um although we're
probably we
we thought we didn't do online sale as
early as 2004
but we do believe that we are our lives
have dramatically changed in terms of
spending and more and more filipinos are
doing the same
buying stuff online rather than
buying uh in malls and i believe and we
believe that this will continue to
happen
even if uh you know when lockdowns are
removed
then simply because we have felt the
convenience already and
you know even if kovid is not here
anymore even if we can go to the malls
we just you know if we have felt already
um
uh the the convenience of buying stuff
online
then we will not be going outside as
much anymore
the third change on technological
disruption is on the left is on the next
slide
and it's the demand for data work from
home
shifts the demand from office space to
digital storage space
video conferencing demands a decent
bandwidth
in the field of healthcare trends like
telemedicine and contract raising
require a heavy digital footprint in the
field of education we have shifted from
going to school to remote learning in
the pa in the philippines for example we
have
you know we have felt this you know
companies schools even homes have now
upgraded their tech
and communications hardware and software
just to accommodate the data demand
uh that is required in living in this
new normal so this is something that
is also changing our lives the fourth
change in technological disruption is in
this next uh
is in the next slide and it's about lean
work forces
manufacturers have been forced to rely
more on automation
uh particularly during kovid and this
will linger on even after the pandemic
simply because automation is more
reliable and companies have
learned that lesson artificial
intelligence and robot
robotics will permeate general purpose
machinery
in areas such as food health care
consumer goods and e-commerce
helping to better insulate companies uh
when it comes to future shocks
like pandemics so this will be something
that will be prevalent as well
now let's look at the second theme uh
outside of the
uh of technological this um disruption
and it's
the globalization and in the
globalization i'd like to
mention two um themes or changes
uh inside this theme that we believe
that will permeate or will be permanent
in the next few years
the one is the change from global travel
to
more local and regional travel we
believe that there's evidence that
travel will be more regional than global
long multinational business junkets will
probably be curtailed
uh while international vacations and
cross-country trips will be
replaced by uh outings closer to home
like um you know instead of flying to
the us most filipinos will be probably
doing um trips uh within uh asean first
and then probably asia
and we believe that this will persist um
uh years even after kovid
and the second item on the globalization
is the decoupling of
the west and china presently uh for
big countries in the west like us and
even japan and europe they import around
of their raw materials from china and it
is only prudent for them to diversify
and obviously
there will be looking for more suppliers
outside of china moving forward
china on the other hand will also they
emphasize their
reliance on western markets um and like
what uh
mr mendoza uh mentioned earlier will be
accelerating their expansion
of their internal value chains and
nurturing their growth within their
economy and they will concentrate more
on consumption
rather than on exports no so this china
will truly transform its economy
and we've known china as the factory of
the world
for so many decades they will change
that and they will become more
uh more of a consumption driven economy
as as they become richer and wealthier
as more millionaires become billionaires
and they they will their economy will
now be reliant on internal
driven factors rather than exports or
trade in general
so the last theme that i'd like to
look at is the is on the next slide and
it's about revisiting policies and
priorities and this is something that
mr mendoza also touched on earlier he
said that you know monetary policy and
fiscal policy will be very
prevalent in the next few years as
economists try to
recover from the pandemic and we believe
that
in this space there will be change now
because
more and more economies are realizing
that monetary policy
will not be enough and they will be
moving to more uh
fiscal policy so this will definitely
affect
areas such as infrastructure spending
education and incentives for
low carbon tech development so this will
be
beneficial to these sectors and the last
item on this theme is the growing demand
for
esg or environmental social and
governance factors
more and more investors are not just
looking at returns
but are also looking at corporate
responsibility
am i investing in a fund that uh buys
stocks of companies that are
not looking at the environment or are or
are
doesn't care about you know if the
community
they uh they uh they they're not um
looking at the interests of stakeholders
like clients employees
shareholders the community and
environment so if they don't i don't
want to exp i don't want to invest in
that fund i want to invest in a fund
that looks at other these other factors
and as such we have seen more than 70
billion dollars net inflows in funds
with
some sort of esg principles embedded
with them and that brought
aum to almost a trillion dollars in
these funds
so let us summarize the impact of these
three trends
and that will be on our next slide so
we'll look first at the impact on the
general or broad asset classes
so we believe that as economy started
open as
uh vaccines are rolled out as um
as uh more and more uh lockdowns are
removed we expect equities to experience
a post-vaccine surge in 2021 just like
what
uh cervix mentioned earlier the u.s is
likely to see
some of the best macroeconomic data it
has seen in years
globally not just in the u.s but
elsewhere supportive loose
monetary and fiscal policy stimulus
stimulus policies
should also help to drive equities
higher that's why
we are preferring equities as a general
asset class as you can see from this
chart
in terms of bonds we are more neutral we
believe that
bonds can offer some protection for
market volatilities however
low and very low negative rates are
right now a very low rates in fact
negative in some areas um this makes it
very uh
this makes bonds uh very um uh
uh the potential for bonds to provide
uh opportunities will be very minimal
further large-scale easing
in rates is is less likely now given the
very low
uh rates that we are already and in the
last asset class that we're like
we're looking at and and and mr mendoza
also touched on this earlier
is that the very low short-term rate
environment that we have
may cash you know your money market your
time deposits
uh your tables all of these short-term
you know semi-guaranteed funds made
they become very attractive at this time
very unattractive this time because of
low interest rates and
and we believe that we we will as an
investor
if you are an investor looking for um uh
investments you should be staying away
from cash
particularly your money that you want to
invest in
for your long-term goals and on the last
slide we'll
we'll show you the specific sectors that
will do well
given the three themes that i mentioned
beforehand
so obviously technology communications
and consumer discretionary will do well
and growth stocks in general will do
well because of the trends that i
mentioned earlier
but we do believe that we need to
balance this with targeted positions in
other sectors uh like like industrials
materials mining and financials just to
be prudent about it
because we believe that there will be
certain values that we can find in this
account in the companies in the sectors
as well
so that ends my presentation um see you
again later for the q a and thank you
[Music]
everyone
and here in manulife china bank life
where you're a seasoned investor or just
starting to build your wealth
we have a range of programs that can
help you grow and diversify your hard
earned money
the good news now is that we just
launched three international new funds
that you may invest in when you get a
life insurance program with us we now
offer
the us growth fund a fund that invests
in some of the largest and most
profitable companies with stocks that
are publicly traded in the united states
some examples of these are alphabet
which is
google's mother company amazon
apple and facebook a lot of us would say
these programs are these uh i'm sorry
these companies are based in the us
and wouldn't really be affecting us here
in the philippines but right now as we
sit at home
you grab out your eye you bring out your
iphone you google something that you
want to buy
you see it on a website you then
get on lazada and purchase it
you pay with visa you know
these are some of the top companies
listed
in the united states stocks in the
united states now
based in the united states so all of
these
are although based abroad
actually affect us here in the
philippines so it's a very interesting
uh proposition for us to be able to
invest in something based abroad that
affects us here you know
the tiger growth fund that we have is
the second fund no it's a fund that
invests in innovative companies that are
publicly traded in both china and hong
kong
samples of these companies are alibaba
and tencent now very
interesting alibaba everybody knows is
one of the largest if not the largest
online purchasing platform in the world
so they've really taken technology to
another level
10 cent if you don't know that what that
is that's the one that does wechat
we pay but more importantly it has
influenced a younger generation of
people who like to play games like
fortnight
clash of clans league of legends they
even invest in movies
and lastly you'll have the option to go
global preferred securities income fund
no
this is when you link an insurance
program in this fund
and with exposure to high quality
securities issued by global companies in
diversified sectors like
banks insurance communication and power
and electric companies
through these funds you can enjoy life
protection while growing your wealth
from across the globe
so if you want to know more about our
products and you have an existing
financial sales associate
please schedule a call or expect a
message from them right after this
webinar
now for those without a financial sales
associate
yet please feel free to get in touch
with the china bank or
mcbl rep who invited you to this webinar
today
or you may reach out to us by visiting
our website
which i believe we will flash on screen
there's a link or you can use the qr
code that you may scan
to visit the mcbl website page
and once again it's still not too late
their audience to hit that q a box and
ask their questions from our speakers
right now we are getting a lot of great
questions from the audience
i'm also excited to hear our guests
answer all these
but before that make sure to stay tuned
until the end of the webinar because
mcbl is giving away gift certificates
worth 5 000
pesos so let's watch out for that at the
end
of the webinar now we're ready we're
ready to bring
back zetted wrecks on screen for our q
and a segment
welcome back boss zed boss rex
good afternoon again hi
good afternoon so gentlemen are you
ready to answer
questions that came out from our q a box
sure okay
boss rex there okay boss rex this one's
for you
for an average person where investing
seems
complicated so to the regular pinoy
how do i start
if we don't know enough i think we have
to
make sure that the commitment is there
to start
knowing something and when i tell people
the the very best way to know something
is to have skin on it i call it the skin
and the game
positioning all i'm saying is this one
if you're not investing in something
there is no propensity for you to really
be motivated to study it
so the key is to start
but it's a very precarious world i mean
if you don't know what you're doing
you're actually going to be losing money
and you're losing money doing the wrong
thing so
the next advice i'll have is to have
a financial advisor it's very different
if you have a partner somebody who deals
with it
as a profession somebody who knows the
market so that
there would be a bit of hand holding at
the start
until number one you're disciplined and
number two you're more knowledgeable
to get on with your own financial
journey
but the more important thing is this
that they have to start somewhere and
they have to start
now and on top of that have somebody
help them out because you know if
there's no one that they can rely on
there can be big mistakes and
i guess as we all say the tuition fee
becomes higher
thank you for that answer bus rex
interesting the tuition fee gets higher
yes
i remember that saying bus zed this one
is for you
what can you say about the philippines
current state of economy in relation to
the philippines stock market
uh that's a good question um we believe
all economies in general
are expected to reopen and hence recover
as soon as the vaccine rollout reach
a large enough portion of the population
and this includes the philippines
definitely so this is not a question of
if but of when but however along the way
there might be short-term headwinds like
uh a temporary surge in cases something
like that
and and while we're sure that somewhere
down the road the philippine economy is
gonna recover we do believe that that
these short-term headwinds will happen
and um
and certex also uh touched on this
earlier as well so this is why we
recommend investors to diversify and
look at getting some exposure to markets
uh that may be well ahead of us in
vaccine rollouts
like the us and china for example wow
noted in that was uh zed though thank
you for that answer
okay uh this question this question next
next question is for bossrex is there a
recommended percentage
for the amount of investments that you
put offshore
sometimes in your total package how much
do you think you should keep
offshore or you should put offshore
that's an interesting question i guess
that comes from someone now
contemplating on
taking a dip on that kind of
diversification globally or maybe
outside the country i can say that the
rule of thumb
is anywhere from 20 to 25
that's a rule of thumb however given our
situation today
i would probably get to increase that by
about
5 to 10 percentage points because of our
situation as zed
said i mean we know we're gonna be left
behind
so if you're going to be allocating more
to the philippines today
certainly your portfolio will not be
performing
as well as a portfolio that's going to
be exposed to
better markets portfolio that's already
uh
into issues and markets that are
already recovering so again going back
to what i said rule of thumb 20 to 25
percent but
be a bit open to increase that a bit
because of
the current kobit situation in the
country
thank you boss rex so 20 to 25 as a rule
of thumb that that that's an interesting
way to look at it right now
you have another question is there a
distinct advantage if the team
managing your funds is based in the
country where the investments are being
made that's a great question and this
um this is basically uh relates to the
three funds you mentioned earlier
me because all of these three funds
their fund managers are actually based
uh where they are domiciled so the u.s
fund
the fund managers in the u.s the china
fund the fund manager is in
uh the tiger fund uh is the fund manager
is inside in is in hong kong
and the global preferred fund the fund
managers in the u.s
were most preferred securities are
issued so yes the
straight answer is definitely yes
there's a distinct advantage
and the key word there is on the ground
you know when you have
uh people research analysts credit
analysts fund managers portfolio
managers
traders who are on the ground they'll
have
you know faster reaction to to news and
updates and anything that
will affect the performance of the fund
and their decisions uh with regards to
stock selection etc so all of these
things are
are very vital um and very important to
the performance of the fund so i believe
that
being on the ground is indeed a distinct
advantage
ah you're i understand
so what you're saying is that when it's
being on the ground they really know
what's happening
real time they can react immediately
interesting uh this next question is for
boss rex
what are the benefits of having offshore
investments
in this time of pandemic that is the
question sir
well i guess we've mentioned that many
many times now both of us me and zed
we said number one it's it's really
diversification
uh you're not going to be uh locked
in on the performance of a given country
in a given economy you're going to be
more spread out
so it's almost like if you have bets
those
bets are in going to are going to be in
in in different
markets uh and in places where
they can better perform the other thing
that
that happens you know when you say
diversification
probably a lot of people are just
looking at market diversification
but there is a natural currency
diversification that also goes with it
see we all know the philippine peso is
very strong today just because the
economy is not doing well
but when the economy starts doing well
when we start to
import goods we start to import raw
materials
you will see that peso weakening again
so
that's a double whammy as far as
exposure is concerned
right so you'll you'll have to uh
lace your portfolio with a stronger
currency
and then that stronger currency would be
the other currencies that
that uh that zed has just mentioned
maybe
um china's currency and the and the
the mighty u.s dollar um the other thing
that that
uh that that's very important is this
zed mentioned that technology is the
driver today i mean it
lords over all industries you take a
look at the philippine market
how many companies can you find that's
going to be
technology focused in the philippines
stock exchange that's going to be very
very little
i can even count them on my fingers but
if you're going to be looking at more
sophisticated markets like
china and the us you'll find a lot of
technology companies
in fact you've mentioned the more
popular ones but
the real other performers are hardware
component makers
chip makers we don't know their names
but they're doing
very very well as well because of their
exposure
to technology
thank you sir interesting interesting
stuff guys
uh another question bossrex for you uh
earlier you mentioned one of the themes
is the quest for yields
on the quest for yields with the
emergence of deposit products
offered by entities like ing
tonic and even g invest that offer high
yields for essentially deposits
would you recommend these over
government securities which
offer approximately one point eight
percent
uh per annum
we have to understand know uh that
every particular investment instrument
is matched with a particular
investment objective sometimes it's very
easy
to think about participating in an
investment because of its higher yields
but let's begin to understand you know
most of these deposit products
are used to practically lure the
customer
i mean it's it's a quest to gain market
share
and when you do that you're actually
going to be increasing your cost
so your deposit rates are going to go up
because you want the clients to come in
but you cannot sustain that
certainly all of these countries all of
these banks all of these other companies
eventually will make it go down to
the more palatable the more acceptable
the more reasonable
rates of deposit
you know you'd want people to get
interested but take note
they have maximum amounts and they'll
probably
as i've said lower this over time so
let's take advantage if we can but uh
it's not going to be
something that would be a focal point in
your investment portfolio
interesting i agree uh at this point i
think that's all the time we have this
afternoon so once again i'd like to
thank our speakers for answering the
questions
now before we let them go on corbuna
i would like to ask if you have any
final tips parting words for our guests
today
let's start with boss zed any parting
words for our guest today boss
ed yeah um i think the key word
that i guess uh that will resonate uh in
today's
webin uh and that resonated in today's
webinar is diversification so
i invite you guys to diversify
your portfolio not
all countries or all asset classes will
do well at any one time
and and it's great to have exposure in
more and more in more countries rather
than just one
and let mcbl be your partner in
diversifying and and
achieving your future goals thank you
very much stay safe everyone
thank you sir zed for uh those
parting words bossrex any party words
from you
of course uh as as uh
zed is mentioned it's an opportune time
it's an important time to revisit
investments to try and diversify but
i guess you know the oldest amongst the
three of us
i can essentially say that i've been
through
several crisis 1997 as mentioned in 2008
and when i look back it is when
this crisis happened that the most money
has been made so i'm i'm
calling on all of the people in our
audience today
think about it don't let this crisis go
to waste
a crisis is an opportunity it's time to
act
you know maybe a lot of you got insights
from today's event
but you have to execute as they say you
know education without execution is mere
entertainment
so please do something call on and just
talk to that person
give him time or her time the person who
invited you this afternoon
and maybe it can be a good step towards
getting into something that will help
you achieve your financial dreams
so thank you for that boss rex
education without execution is only
entertainment i'm going to write that
down later so thank you for that
um thank you once again to bos rex boss
zed
it was indeed a very insightful
afternoon
i hope you guys are still with us
because we will now be raffling off 5
pesos worth of sodexo gift certificates
to one
lucky registrant so normally i would
probably pull the name out of her hat
but we have that prepared
congratulations to miss kathy c miss
kathy c
you are our winner for 5 000 pesos worth
of sodexo gift certificates
um please uh stay tuned or our
representative from mcbl will get in
touch with you soon on how you can claim
your price so congratulations miss
kathy c you have won 5 000 pesos worth
of sodexo gift
certificates thank you so now
we'd like to thank everyone who joined
us this afternoon for taking time out
and for
actively participating during the
webinar during our q a segment
during our poll as you set your
short-term and long-term financial goals
we hope that our offshore investment
funds can help you achieve the financial
success
you and your you wish for yourself and
your family
and that wraps up this afternoon's
financial wellness webinar this has been
your host mr wamejana we hope to see you
in our future webinars uh we'd also like
to hear your feedback on this
afternoon's webinar
simply scan the qr code being flashed on
your screen
and kindly spend time to answer our
two-minute survey
maraming stay safe everyone and have a
nice weekend
see you all
[Music]
manulife and china bank
two companies you can trust two top
institutions in the financial industry
teammates partners working together to
handle
every aspect of your finances from day
to day
to your future plans personalized to
your story
so you're ready for life's every twist
and turn
we have you covered starting with your
kids dreams
to providing a secure future for your
family
working to build your wealth and
ensuring your wealth
works for you always with you in
sickness and in health
through the best times and the worst all
just for you
let us be your partner manulife china
bank life
life with a plan let us help you get
started
today
you deserve the best life you work hard
you know the formula for success
your options are wide but few make the
cut
we can help you make the most out of
life
because you deserve the privilege that
comes with building an elite life
introducing manulife china bank life
affluence max
elite this one-time investment in life
insurance plan
provides you with a startup bonus that
would optimize your funds on the onset
so you can enjoy
rewards now and in the future
[Music]
experience the manulife china bank life
advantage
let's say you put in a one-time
investment of 1 million pesos
manulife china bank life will give you
one percent of that
as a start-up bonus this increases your
investment by ten thousand pesos
get a loyalty bonus if you stay invested
you may have the chance to get a loyalty
bonus on the 10th
15th and on the 20th year
[Music]
enjoy hassle-free application through a
guaranteed issue offer
[Music]
this means that there would be no need
for medical examinations if certain
conditions
are met get a boost on your investment
by making additional investments anytime
enjoy peace of mind with life insurance
coverage
invest through manulife china bank life
affluence
max elite get an early reward
and look forward to more
[Music]
you